<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ordinance for continuing the excise</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Lord Protector (1653-1658 : O. Cromwell)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7128A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1063_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209526</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868402</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868402</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169167</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169167)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 158:E1063[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ordinance for continuing the excise</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Lord Protector (1653-1658 : O. Cromwell)</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Council of State.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>3, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills, Printer to His Highness the Lord Protector,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Order to print dated: 24 December 1653.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Excise tax --  England --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:169167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:169167:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169167:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon of the Commonwealth</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>AN ORDINANCE for continuing the EXCISE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the time for recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Duty of Exciſe and New Impoſt, is neer expiration, and it being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the peace and ſafety of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth that the ſame be continued, both for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the publick Debts charged upon the ſaid Grand Receipt, as alſo for carrying on the weighty Affairs of this Commonwealth, His Highneſs the Lord Protector, with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Conſent of his Council, doth Ordain,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169167:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->and be it Ordained, That all and every the Acts, Ordinances, and Orders of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment touching the Exciſe, and every Clauſe, Sentence and Article in them or any of them contained, and now in force, aſwel for the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting, gathering and receiving, as concerning the Government and Ordering of the Exciſe and New Impoſt, be continued, and the Duty of Exciſe and New Impoſt, according to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Rates in them, or any of them expreſſed, be recived, collected and paid in and through <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town and Port of <hi>Barwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> untill the five and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyeth day of <hi>March</hi> next comming; And that <hi>Luke Hodges, Thomas Bulſtrode,</hi> &amp; <hi>William Parker,</hi> or any two or more of them, be and are hereby conſtituted and appointed Commiſſioners of the Grand Exciſe and New Impoſt, and are hereby impowred and authorized to exerciſe and put in execution all and every the Powers and Authorities given or granted by, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in all or any the ſaid Acts, Ordinances, or Orders of Parliament, touching the Exciſe and New Impoſt, as well for the collecting and receiving the Several Rates aforeſaid, as concerning the Government &amp; Ordering of the ſaid Exciſe and New Impoſt, as fully and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply as any Commiſſioners for Exciſe, at the time of the making of this preſent Ordinance, may or ought to have done, and ſhall obſerve ſuch further Orders and Directions as they ſhall from time to time receive from His Highneſs the Lord Protector, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, touching the ſame; And for their Care, Paines, and Service therein, they ſhall have one penny in every twenty ſhillings raiſed and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169167:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
levyed for Exciſe and New Impoſt. Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nevertheleſs, and it is hereby declared, that from and after the nine and twentyth day of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 1653. The Commiſſioners afore-named ſhall not let to farm, or admit any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to farm the Exciſe of any Goods, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes and Manufactures that are exciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by any Act, Ordinance, or Order of Parliament, without the Order and Direction of ſuch Perſons as ſhall be appointed thereunto by His Highneſſe the Lord Protector, and his Council, But the ſaid Commiſſioners, or any two or more of them, ſhall mannage and carry on the ſame, according to the beſt of their Iudgements, by ſuch good Wayes and Means as may be moſt for the Eaſe of the People, and Advantage of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <div type="license">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Saturday</hi> the 24. of <hi>December</hi> 1653.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>Ordered by His Highneſs the Lord Protector, and his Council, That this Ordinance be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>HEN. SCOBEL Clerk of the Council.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Lord Protector. 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
